<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">PeerJ</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PeerJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">16</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.16</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="categories">
          <subject>Biophysics</subject>
          <subject>Computational Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title><named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content>/<named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> selectivity in the bacterial voltage-gated sodium channel NavAb</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group content-type="authors">
        <contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Corry</surname>
            <given-names>Ben</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp-1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff-1"><institution>Research School of Biology</institution>, <addr-line>The Australian National University</addr-line>, <addr-line>Acton</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group content-type="editors">
        <contrib id="editor-1" contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Separovic</surname>
            <given-names>Frances</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="corresp-1">
          <label>*</label>
          <email>ben.corry@anu.edu.au</email>
        </corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2013-02-12">
        <day>12</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>1</volume>
      <elocation-id>e16</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2012-11-30">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2013-01-04">
          <day>4</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2013 Corry</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Corry</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/16"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>The recent publication of a number of high resolution bacterial voltage-gated sodium channel structures has opened the door for the mechanisms employed by these channels to distinguish between ions to be elucidated. The way these channels select between <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">K<sup>+</sup></named-content> has been investigated in computational studies, but the selectivity for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> over <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> has not yet been studied in this way. Here we use molecular dynamics simulations to calculate the energetics of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> transport through the channel. Single ion profiles show that <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> experiences a large barrier midway through the selectivity filter that is not seen by <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content>. This barrier is caused by the need for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> to partly dehydrate to pass through this region and the lack of compensating interactions with the protein. Multi-ion profiles show that ions can pass each other in the channel, which is why the presence of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> does not block <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> conduction despite binding more strongly in the pore.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <kwd>Ion channel</kwd>
        <kwd>Ion selectivity</kwd>
        <kwd>Molecular dynamics</kwd>
        <kwd>Sodium channel</kwd>
        <kwd>Action potential</kwd>
        <kwd>Bacterial channel</kwd>
        <kwd>Calcium channel</kwd>
        <kwd>Simulation</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group id="fund-1">
          <funding-source>Pawsey Centre Project</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group id="fund-2">
          <funding-source>Merit Allocation Scheme of the NCI</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by computer time from the Pawsey Centre Project in Western Australia and through an award under the Merit Allocation Scheme of the NCI facility at the ANU. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Voltage-gated sodium channels create the upstroke of action potentials in excitable cells by opening a <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> selective transmembrane pore in response to small depolarising signals. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-5">Catterall, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-17">Goldin, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-21">Hille, 2001</xref>) These channels are able to rapidly move <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> ions down their electrochemical gradient, while limiting the passage of other ions such as <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">K<sup>+</sup></named-content>, <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Cl<sup>−</sup></named-content>. Until recently, gaining a detailed understanding of the mechanisms leading to ion selectivity in these channels has been difficult due to a lack of structural information. The publication of atomic resolution structures of a number of voltage-gated sodium channels from bacteria in the last 18 months (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-28">McCusker et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-32">Payandeh et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-31">Payandeh et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-52">Zhang et al., 2012</xref>) has, however, now made it possible to elucidate the physical mechanisms employed to generate sodium selectivity.</p>
      <p>Unlike eukaryotic sodium channels that are formed from a single protein chain, the bacterial sodium channels are made up of four identical subunits that surround a central pore. The pore shape is similar to the familiar structure of potassium channels. One set of transmembrane helices form an inverted tepee that lines the inner half of the pore and contains the activation gate. A re-entrant loop between two short helices forms a narrow ‘selectivity filter’ that is wider and shorter than that of potassium channels, as well as being partly lined by amino acid side chains. In these bacterial sodium channels, four identical subunits line the pore and the external end of the filter is surrounded by side chains of four glutamate residues (Glu177), in the same sequence position as the characteristic DEKA ring found in eukaryotic sodium channels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-31">Payandeh et al., 2011</xref>) which is known from mutation studies to be essential in creating <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> selectivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-13">Favre, Moczydlowski &amp; Schild, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-19">Heinemann et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-41">Sun et al., 1997</xref>).</p>
      <p>The question of how the bacterial sodium channels can discriminate between <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">K<sup>+</sup></named-content> has been addressed in studies based upon the crystal structure of the channel from <italic>Arcobacter butzleri</italic> (NavAb) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-31">Payandeh et al., 2011</xref>). It was initially suggested that the high field strength of the glutamate residues would create an ion binding site more favourable for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> than <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">K<sup>+</sup></named-content> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-31">Payandeh et al., 2011</xref>). Two computational studies, however, highlighted the importance of a narrow region just beyond this binding site for creating selectivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-10">Corry &amp; Thomas, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-15">Furini &amp; Domene, 2012</xref>). We have suggested that the discrimination at this point arises from the inability of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">K<sup>+</sup></named-content> to fit through the narrow region of the pore along with surrounding water molecules in the optimal geometry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-10">Corry &amp; Thomas, 2012</xref>).</p>
      <p>How ion channels discriminate between <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> is also not straight forward to explain. The family of voltage-gated sodium channels is closely related to the voltage-gated calcium channels. They share a similar topology comprising four homologous domains each containing 6 transmembrane sections. Furthermore, both classes of channel are believed to share some structural features in the selectivity filter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-21">Hille, 2001</xref>). Mutation of a few key residues in both eukaryotic and bacterial sodium channels can decrease or reverse <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> selectivity to create a pore with characteristics similar to the voltage-gated calcium channels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-19">Heinemann et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-37">Shaya et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-41">Sun et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-51">Yue et al., 2002</xref>). Similarly, substitutions in the conserved ‘EEEE locus’ of calcium selective channels can allow <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> permeation or remove <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> currents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-6">Cibulsky &amp; Sather, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-12">Ellinor et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-42">Tang et al., 1993</xref>). Thus the difference in selectivity seen in sodium and calcium channels appears to be due to only minor differences in the protein.</p>
      <p>A number of computational studies made in the absence of atomic resolution information have examined the nature of selection between <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2">Boda et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-7">Corry et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-8">Corry et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-9">Corry &amp; Chung, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-11">Corry, Vora &amp; Chung, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-16">Gillespie, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-30">Nonner, Catacuzzeno &amp; Eisenberg, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-47">Vora, Corry &amp; Chung, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-50">Yang, Henderson &amp; Busath, 2004</xref>). It has been suggested, for example, that the electrostatic interactions that bind <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> differently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-8">Corry et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-9">Corry &amp; Chung, 2006</xref>) or the simple competition between differently charged ions for a limited space (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-30">Nonner, Catacuzzeno &amp; Eisenberg, 2000</xref>) can be enough to explain the different behaviours of sodium and calcium channels, but these ideas are yet to be tested in models containing atomic detail. Experimental studies have shown that eukaryotic calcium channels are continually occupied by at least one <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> that guards against permeation of other ions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-20">Hess &amp; Tsien, 1984</xref>).</p>
      <p>How NavAb distinguishes between <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> has not yet been explained, and this manuscript aims to address this issue. <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content>currents are more than 20 times greater than <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> currents in NavAb when measured without the other ion present (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-31">Payandeh et al., 2011</xref>). Reversal potentials of the closely related NachBac and NavSp1 channels measured in asymmetric solutions show a preference for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> over <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> of 7–15 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-37">Shaya et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-51">Yue et al., 2002</xref>). These two ions are very similar in size, yet differ in charge, and so the mechanism of selectivity must rely of the consequences of this charge difference. Further confusing this issue is that a ring of four glutamate residues has been found to be essential to create <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> over <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> selectivity in calcium channels, so one can ask why the presence of the ring of glutamates present in the bacterial sodium channels does not yield <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> selectivity. Here we employ the recent structural information in molecular dynamics simulations to try to understand why the passage of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> is preferred over <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> in the bacterial voltage-gated sodium channel NavAB.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <p>Protein coordinates were obtained from the protein database, PDB accession code 3RVY (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-31">Payandeh et al., 2011</xref>). Only the pore forming region from residue 115 to 221 was included in the simulations. In order to conduct the molecular dynamics simulations, the protein was placed in a pre-equilibrated POPC lipid bilayer, solvated in a 72 × 72 × 82 Å box of TIP3P water with 250 mM NaCl, yielding a system with approximately 41,000 atoms as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>. The protein was initially held fixed while the lipid and water were allowed to equilibrate for 2 ns, before the protein alpha carbons were restrained with a harmonic potential of force constant decreasing from 10 to 0.01 kcal/mol in 8 steps each lasting 1 ns. To account for the lipid molecules protruding into the centre of the pore in the crystal structure, the tails of four lipid molecules were restrained to the crystallographic positions with a force constant slowly increasing during the period in which the protein was restrained. During data collection they were restrained with a force constant of 0.1 kcal/mol/Å<sup>2</sup>. A final 15 ns of equilibration were conducted at the final restraint values. In longer unrestrained simulations not described here, lipid remains constantly present in the lateral phenestrations. For the simulations involving <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>, one <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> was replaced with <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> and an additional <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Cl<sup>−</sup></named-content> added to neutralise the system.</p>
      <fig id="fig-1">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.16/fig-1</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Simulation system.</title>
          <p>A cross section of the simulation system is shown, with two of the four protein chains shown in purple, lipid in brown, <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> in yellow, <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Cl<sup>−</sup></named-content> in green and the volume sampled by water molecules indicated by the transparent surface.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/16/fig-1.png"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Potentials of mean force (PMF) were calculated using umbrella sampling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-46">Torrie &amp; Valleau, 1974</xref>). To ensure other ions did not enter the selectivity filter during these simulations, all other ions were kept out of a sphere of radius 13 Å centred on the middle of the selectivity filter using harmonic repulsive potential with force constant 40 kcal/mol/Å<sup>2</sup>. When making 1 ion PMFs, the axial separation (<italic>z</italic>) of the ion of interest and the centre of mass of the alpha carbons of the selectivity filter (residues 175–178) was restrained in 0.25 Å steps in the <italic>z</italic>-direction with a force constant of 12 kcal/mol/Å<sup>2</sup>. For the two ion PMFs a force constant of 7 kcal/mol/Å<sup>2</sup> and 0.5 Å steps were employed. Simulations lasting 2 ns were conducted at each window, with the first ns regarded as equilibration time and analysis conducted on only the second ns. Thus each single ion PMF involves 101 simulations for a total of 202 ns. The 2 ion <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>/<named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> PMF involves 695 simulations for a total of 1390 ns. To reduce the amount of equilibration time required in each umbrella window, a number of starting coordinates were generated in which one or two ions were swapped with equilibrated water molecules throughout the length of the pore. In the two ion case, this meant starting coordinates were generated with the ions separated by integer numbers of water molecules. Collective analysis was made with the weighted histogram analysis method. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-24">Kumar et al. (1992)</xref> using the implementation of Grossfield (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-18">Grossfield</xref>). The axial coordinate used in all the graphs is zeroed at the position of the centre of mass of the alpha carbons of the selectivity filter. The single <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> PMF was obtained three times from three independent sets of simulations to gain an idea of the reproducibility of the results.</p>
      <p>Unless otherwise stated, all simulations employed the CHARMM27 force field with CMAP correction for the protein and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-25">MacKerell et al., 1998</xref>) CHARMM36 for lipids, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-23">Klauda et al., 2010</xref>) and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Cl<sup>−</sup></named-content> parameters from Joung (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-22">Joung &amp; Cheatham, 2008</xref>). Because of the uncertainties involved in using a non-polarisable force field to describe interactions with <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>, care should be taken not to overemphasise quantitative results involving this ion. Simulations were conducted with NAMD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-33">Phillips et al., 2005</xref>) with periodic boundary conditions using the particle mesh Ewald scheme for calculating electrostatic interactions, a 1 fs time-step at constant pressure (1 atm) and temperature (298 K) (NPT ensemble). A harmonic potential of 0.01 kcal/mol/Å<sup>2</sup> was held on the alpha-carbon atoms, except for those forming the selectivity filter (residues 174–183) during data production. Coordination numbers were defined as the number of non-hydrogen atoms within 3.0 Å of the ion, the approximate position of the first minimum in the bulk ion–water oxygen radial distribution function.</p>
      <p>To calculate the dehydration energies of the ions, we used the method of alchemical free energy perturbation (FEP) following the approach previously taken to examine partial dehydration of monovalent ions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-38">Song &amp; Corry, 2009</xref>). To create a dehydration scenario similar to that for ions entering the channel, we first generated a water sphere of radius 15 Å with the test ion fixed at the center to represent the bulk solution. Beside this (20 Å from the center of the large sphere) we placed a smaller water sphere of radius 3.2 Å that contained the desired number of water molecules. Large constraints (100 kcal/mol Å<sup>2</sup>) were applied to keep all of the atoms in the constant-volume spheres, as was done previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-45">Thomas, Jayatilaka &amp; Corry, 2007</xref>). Then, alchemical FEP calculations were performed for these systems in which the test ion was moved from the bulk–water sphere to the small water cluster, replacing a water molecule that was moved in the opposite direction. All simulation parameters except for the force field parameters for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> are the same as our previous study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-38">Song &amp; Corry, 2009</xref>). To calculate the cost of removing water beyond the second solvation shell a similar procedure was conducted except, the small sphere had a radius of 6 Å and contained 32 water molecules, the average number found within the first and second solvation shells for both ions in bulk simulations. Each FEP calculation was repeated 9 times and the results show the average free energy change and the standard error in the mean.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>The single ion PMFs for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref> show that both ions are attracted from bulk (at the right side of the figure) into the selectivity filter of the channel and have an energy minimum adjacent to the ring of Glu177 residues at around <italic>z</italic> = 5 Å. In this position each ion is directly coordinated by the side chains of one glutamate residue as well as that of Ser178 as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Figs. 3A and 3C</xref> and evident in a plot of ion coordination numbers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4</xref>). <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> binds more strongly to the protein than <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> as evidenced by the greater difference in the free energy of the binding site relative to bulk. Unlike in previous MD studies of a model pore containing four glutamate residues in which the <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> binds centrally coordinated by multiple carboxylate groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-50">Yang, Henderson &amp; Busath, 2004</xref>), here the ion directly coordinates to only one glu side chain. Part of the reason for this is likely to be that each of the glu side chains is held in position by hydrogen bonds to Ser 1180 and Met 1181 on the helix further from the pore.</p>
      <fig id="fig-2">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.16/fig-2</object-id>
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Single ion potential of mean force.</title>
          <p>Single ion potential of mean force (PMF) for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content>(blue), <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>(red) and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">K<sup>+</sup></named-content>(black dashed line) is shown as a function of the axial position of the ion, zeroed at the centre of the selectivity filter. The ion is in bulk water at the right side of the graph and in the central cavity of the channel on the left hand side. For <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> the PMF shown is the average of 3 independent sets of simulations, with the standard deviation in the three values shown shaded in grey.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/16/fig-2.png"/>
      </fig>
      <p>To pass further into the pore, an ion must leave the embrace of the glutamate side chains. We have previously suggested that it is the unfavourable location where the ion passes through the plane of these side chains at which selectivity for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> over <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">K<sup>+</sup></named-content> arises (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-10">Corry &amp; Thomas, 2012</xref>). As for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">K<sup>+</sup></named-content>, <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> experiences an energy barrier at this position.</p>
      <p>In contrast to both <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">K<sup>+</sup></named-content>, <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> experiences a large energy barrier further into the pore, at around <italic>z</italic> = 0.5 Å in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>, which it must overcome to enter the central cavity of the pore. The size of the maximum energy barrier seen by each ion type (Na<sup>+</sup> &lt; K<sup>+</sup> &lt; Ca<sup>2+</sup>) is in accord with the magnitude of current measured for each ion (Na<sup>+</sup> &gt; K<sup>+</sup> &gt; Ca<sup>2+</sup>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-31">Payandeh et al., 2011</xref>). The energy change for an ion to move from the energy minimum in the filter to the start of the central cavity is about 1 kcal/mol for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> and 3 kcal/mol for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>, reinforcing that <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> binds more strongly in the filter than <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content>. The single <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> PMF was obtained 3 times from 3 independent sets of simulations to gain an appreciation of the reproducibility of the results. In all cases the maximum barrier for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> permeation occurs at the same location near <italic>z</italic> = 0.5 Å.</p>
      <p>To conduct our simulations we use the ‘pre-open’ structure of the channel, in which the selectivity filter is believed to be in an open state, but the activation gate is closed at the intracellular end of the pore (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-31">Payandeh et al., 2011</xref>). As a consequence, a large increase in free energy is seen at the left hand end of the PMFs shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref> where the ion approaches the closed gate, and energy values in this region cannot be expected to represent those in a fully open channel. While it is possible that the closed gate could alter the energy profiles in the filter, we expect that the water filled cavity to largely screen the effect of the gate on the energy values in the filter.</p>
      <p>To understand the reason for the large energetic barrier seen by <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>, we show a snapshot of either <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> or <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> in this position in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Figs. 3B and 3D</xref>. Here, the ion has moved beyond the Glu177 side chains, but not so far into the pore as to be surrounded by the backbone carbonyls of Thr175 and Leu176 which have been suggested to form an ideal environment for a solvated ion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-31">Payandeh et al., 2011</xref>). Rather, the ion is surrounded by 5 or 6 water molecules which can only form limited interactions with the protein. Inspection of the coordination numbers of the ions in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4</xref> shows that <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> maintains a coordination number close to 6 as it passes through this part of the pore, and begins to form occasional contacts with the backbone carbonyl groups. The coordination number of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>, however, shows 2 regions at which it drops below the average value of 7. When adjacent to the Glu177 residues, the coordination number begins to drop (labelled ① in the figure), but the strong interaction with the charged residues means this remains a favourable location for the ion. There is another significant drop at the location of the energy barrier (labelled ②) to a value less than 6.5.</p>
      <fig id="fig-3">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.16/fig-3</object-id>
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Snapshots of ions in the channel.</title>
          <p>Simulation snapshots showing the ion and coordinating water when either <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> (A) or <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> (C) is at the external binding site, or when the <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> (B) and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> (D) is at the location of the largest barrier experienced by <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/16/fig-3.png"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="fig-4">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.16/fig-4</object-id>
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Coordination numbers of ions in the channel.</title>
          <p>Coordination numbers for (A) <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> and (B) <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> as a function of the axial position of the ion in the pore. The total coordination number is shown in black, while the contribution from water (blue), glutamate side chains (red) and other protein residues (green) are indicated. Standard errors in the mean are smaller than the data points and are not shown.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/16/fig-4.png"/>
      </fig>
      <p>In <xref ref-type="table" rid="table-1">Table 1</xref>, we show the energetic cost of removing water from the hydration shell of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> to see if this can account for the energy barriers seen in our PMFs. For <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content>, the penalty for removing a single water from the inner hydration shell costs ∼3  kcal/mol. In contrast, <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> holds on to both its inner and outer solvation shells much more strongly due to the increased electrostatic interactions of this ion with water molecules. From <xref ref-type="table" rid="table-1">Table 1</xref> it can be seen that removing one water molecule from the inner shell of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> (going from a coordination number of 7 to 6) has an energy cost of ∼8  kcal/mol. This suggests that removal of (on average) half a water molecule from the solvation shell could account for half the energy barrier seen by <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>. The results in table also show that <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> is sensitive to the environment outside the immediate coordination shell and so it is plausible that changes in the first solvation shell and limited interactions with more distant water could account for the barrier seen in our PMFs.</p>
      <table-wrap id="table-1">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.16/table-1</object-id>
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Free energy (kcal/mol) required to partly dehydrate each type of ion. Each value represents the energy to remove an ion from bulk to a situation in which it is surrounded either by <italic>n</italic> water molecules or its first and second solvation shell (column labelled 2nd shell) as determined from FEP simulations. The bracketed values show the standard error in the mean for the last digit calculated from 9 independent simulations.</p>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/16/table-1.png"/>
          <table>
            <colgroup>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left"/>
                <th align="center" colspan="8">
                  <italic>n</italic>
                </th>
                <th align="left"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th align="left"/>
                <th align="left">0</th>
                <th align="left">1</th>
                <th align="left">2</th>
                <th align="left">3</th>
                <th align="left">4</th>
                <th align="left">5</th>
                <th align="left">6</th>
                <th align="left">7</th>
                <th align="left">2nd Shell</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content>
                </td>
                <td align="left">71.2 (1)</td>
                <td align="left">47.2 (2)</td>
                <td align="left">32.5 (2)</td>
                <td align="left">20.9 (3)</td>
                <td align="left">11.9 (3)</td>
                <td align="left">6.7 (2)</td>
                <td align="left">4.0 (3)</td>
                <td align="left">N/A</td>
                <td align="left">−0.1 (0.2)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>
                </td>
                <td align="left">312.2 (6)</td>
                <td align="left">247.8 (9)</td>
                <td align="left">200 (1)</td>
                <td align="left">161.6 (6)</td>
                <td align="left">123.6 (7)</td>
                <td align="left">95 (1)</td>
                <td align="left">71.4 (6)</td>
                <td align="left">63.6 (7)</td>
                <td align="left">11.7 (7)</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>To further support our claim that the differences in coordination numbers can account for the different free energy barriers seen by the ions in the channel, we plot the average ion–water and ion–protein interaction energy as a function of ion position for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> in the selectivity filter in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">Fig. 5A</xref>. The ion–protein and ion–water interactions are almost mirror images of one another. It can be seen that a strong attractive interaction between the ion and protein arises when the ion is close to the ring of Glu177 residues (<italic>z</italic> = 5 Å). At this point, the replacement of water in the coordination shell with protein yields a less negative ion–water interaction. As the ion moves through the centre of the selectivity filter, the ion–protein interaction becomes less negative and the ion–water interaction more negative. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">Fig. 5B</xref> we plot the sum of the ion–protein and ion–water interactions as either a single <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> or <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> moves through the pore (vertically shifted so the results for the two ions can be compared). The fact that the two interaction terms are almost mirror images means that the sum of the two produces a relatively flat line. While the sum of the interactions fluctuates as a function of ion position, it is much more stable for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> than for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>. At the location of the energy barrier for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> seen in the PMFs (<italic>z</italic> = 0.5 Å), both ions see an upward deflection in the curve, indicating that the ion–protein interaction is not able to compensate for the reduced ion–water interaction that is enforced by the limited space in the pore. Reinforcing the conclusion drawn from the graph of coordination numbers, the barrier seen for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> seems to be due to a less than ideal combination of ion–protein and ion–water interactions. In other words, <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> experiences a degree of dehydration which is not compensated by interactions with the protein. The second and further hydration shells are also held more strongly by <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> than <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content>, and so their removal will also disfavour <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> as this does not appear to be compensated by interactions with the protein.</p>
      <fig id="fig-5">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.16/fig-5</object-id>
        <label>Figure 5</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Interaction energies of the ions with water and protein when in the channel.</title>
          <p>Ion–water and ion–protein interaction energies. (A) the <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>–protein (black) and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>–water (blue) interaction is plotted as a function of the axial position of the ion in the pore. (B) The sum of the ion–water and ion–protein interaction energies is shown for both <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> (blue) and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> (red) as a function of the axial position of the ion in the pore. As only changes in the total energy with position are important for the discussion presented, the curves on B have been vertically shifted to zero at the left hand side to allow for the results for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> to be more easily compared.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/16/fig-5.png"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Having described the differences in the permeation of a single <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> and a single <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> ion through the channel, we next turn our attention to what would occur if multiple ions are allowed to enter the pore. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">Fig. 6</xref> we plot the PMF as a function of the position of two <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> ions in the pore. This graph is generated from the same data presented in our previous work, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-10">Corry &amp; Thomas, 2012</xref>) and shows how the presence of two <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> ions can slightly reduce the barriers to ion conduction compared to the case when a single ion permeates on its own. The plot shows that one ion is likely to always occupy the binding site by the Glu177 residues and that conduction is most likely to occur when a second ion displaces the first ion from this position and pushes it through the pore in a loosely coupled knock on mechanism (i.e., following the dotted line from state 1 to 2 to 3 as shown in the insets to the figure). The maximum barrier for this process is approximately 2.5 kcal/mol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-10">Corry &amp; Thomas, 2012</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">Figure 6</xref> also shows that it is possible for a <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> ion to bypass a resident ion (crossing the diagonal on the plot).The energy barrier for this process is only 2 kcal/mol greater than that seen for knock on conduction. Thus, ions may be able to pass each other in the pore and so conduction may not be a strictly single file process.</p>
      <fig id="fig-6">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.16/fig-6</object-id>
        <label>Figure 6</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Potential of mean force for two sodium ions in the channel.</title>
          <p>The PMF is plotted as a function of the positions of two <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> ions in the pore. Contours are at 1 kcal/mol intervals. Representative snapshots are shown in the insets for three low energy configurations, whose locations are shown on the plot. The approximate lowest energy pathway for ion permeation is shown by the dotted line.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/16/fig-6.png"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The PMF obtained with two <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> ions in the channel is plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">Fig. 7</xref>. The barrier for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> conduction is lowered by the presence of the second ion, as can be seen by the reduced barrier to move along the path indicated by the dotted line compared to moving along the top edge of the figure. The maximum barrier for conduction drops from ∼8 kcal/mol in the single ion PMF to ∼4.5 in the two ion case, more consistent with the observation that <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> currents are 20 fold less than <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> currents. Thus, <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> will also be expected to conduct in a knock on mechanism. The largest barrier to permeation is located at the same position as for the single ion PMF (<italic>z</italic> = 0.5 Å), indicating that the analysis of the origin of this barrier is relevant in the case of multi-ion conduction. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">Figure 7</xref> also indicates that <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> ions are unlikely to pass each other in the pore.</p>
      <fig id="fig-7">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.16/fig-7</object-id>
        <label>Figure 7</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Potential of mean force for two calcium ions in the channel.</title>
          <p>Two ion potential of mean force for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>. The PMF is plotted as a function of the positions of two <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> ions in the pore. Contours are at 1 kcal/mol intervals. Representative snapshots are shown in the insets for four low energy configurations, whose locations are shown on the plot. The approximate lowest energy pathway for ion permeation is shown by the dotted line. A smaller range of coordinates is shown compared to the other two ion PMFs as the ions are unlikely to pass each other in the pore.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/16/fig-7.png"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="fig-8">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.16/fig-8</object-id>
        <label>Figure 8</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Potential of mean force for one calcium and one sodium ion in the channel.</title>
          <p>Mixed ion potential of mean force. The PMF is plotted as a function of the position of one <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> ion (<italic>x</italic>-axis) and one <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> ion (<italic>y</italic>-axis). Contours are at 1 kcal/mol intervals. Representative snapshots are shown in the insets for six low energy configurations whose locations are shown on the plot. The approximate lowest energy pathway for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> to permeate through the pore by passing a resident <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> ion is shown by the dotted line.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/16/fig-8.png"/>
      </fig>
      <p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">Fig. 8</xref> we show the PMF in a mixture of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content>. If we start with the <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> adjacent to Glu177 (as depicted in inset 3) then we can see than the barrier for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> to move through the channel is no smaller with <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> nearby (moving from the state shown in inset 3 to inset 1) than if <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> is moving on its own (state 3 to state 2). In each case the maximum barrier is ∼6.5  kcal/mol, which is similar to that seen in the single ion <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>PMF. The figure also shows the profile for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> to bypass <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> (i.e., moving along the dotted line from state 3 to 4 to 5 to 6). Here the maximum barrier of ∼5  kcal/mol arises at the point at which the ions move past one another (between states 4 and 5). Thus, it is more likely for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> to bypass <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> than for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> to be pushed through the pore. Finally we can see that if <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> starts in the pore (state 5) then <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> can easily displace it and push it through the pore (state 6).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In the absence of other cations, our simulations imply that the conduction of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> is rapid due to the small energy barriers experienced by these moving through the pore in a sequential knock on process. In contrast, we see a much larger barrier for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> to pass, in accord with its lower current. The barrier for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> is slightly lower in the presence of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> and is further lowered in the presence of a second <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>.</p>
      <p>The results shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">Figs. 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">8</xref>, however, also indicate that ions can pass each other inside the pore. When two <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> ions are in the pore (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">Fig. 6</xref>) the barrier for ions passing each other is only a little larger than seen for knock on conduction, while <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> can pass <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">K<sup>+</sup></named-content> with almost no additional barrier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-10">Corry &amp; Thomas, 2012</xref>). If <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> resides in the pore, the entry of a <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> ion does not increase the likelihood of the <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>passing through the pore. <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> can also move around a resident <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> ion and conduct through the pore, however the barrier for this process is larger than when only <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> is present. As a consequence, we would expect the presence of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> in the filter to attenuate <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> currents, but not to completely prevent them.</p>
      <p>It has previously been shown that divalent cations interfere with the conduction of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> in eukaryotic sodium channels. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-14">French et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-29">Mozhayeva, Naumov &amp; Khodorov, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-34">Ravindran, Schild &amp; Moczydlowski, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-43">Tanguy &amp; Yeh, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-44">Taylor, Armstrong &amp; Bezanilla, 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-48">Woodhull, 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-49">Yamamoto, Yeh &amp; Narahashi, 1984</xref>) But, in the bacterial channel NachBac, the presence of 1 mM <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> only slightly reduces <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> currents, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-35">Ren et al., 2001</xref>) This could only arise if either <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> did not enter the pore or if <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> can pass <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> ions resident in the pore. Our simulations results would suggest a larger attenuation of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> currents in the presence of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> in NavAb than seen experimentally for NachBac. While it is possible that these channels are different in this respect, the sequence similarity of the two proteins makes this seem unlikely. The proximity of the four Glu177 residues makes it possible that one or more of these residues will be protonated as is suspected to be the case in calcium channels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-8">Corry et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-36">Root &amp; Mackinnon, 1994</xref>). Previously we suggested that the protonation of a single Glu side chain would not influence the selectivity of the channel for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> over <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">K<sup>+</sup></named-content>, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-10">Corry &amp; Thomas, 2012</xref>) however, this does reduce the strength of binding of the ion to the external site. The position of the saddle point in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">Fig. 7</xref> shows that the easiest way for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> to pass a resident <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> is for the <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> ion to back slightly out of the binding site. Any reduction in affinity of the site would make it easier for a resident <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> ion to do this. This, in turn, may expediate the passage of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> past a resident <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>, and thus limit the attenuation of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> currents seen in the presence of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>.</p>
      <p>Another important factor to consider is how accurately the classical simulations used here can be expected to reproduce the free energies of the transport process. Ideally, the ion parameters need to be able to reproduce the interactions of the ions with a range of molecules (including protein functional groups and water) as well as the structure and dynamics of interacting molecules, something which is difficult to achieve with classical non-polarisable models. Dealing with divalent ions is particularly difficult in non-polar force fields. Due their high charge density, divalent ions are more likely to polarise surrounding molecules than is the case for monovalent ions, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1">Bako, Hutter &amp; Palinkas, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3">Bucher &amp; Kuyucak, 2008</xref>) an effect which is not considered in the present study. The parameters for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">K<sup>+</sup></named-content> have been shown to accurately reproduce a range of properties including hydration energies, the structures of ion–water clusters and crystals and binding energies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-22">Joung &amp; Cheatham, 2008</xref>). The parameters for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> were also optimised to reproduce hydration free energies and binding energies with water, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-26">Marchand &amp; Roux, 1998</xref>) and have been used in a range of studies of biological molecules, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-4">Cates, Teodoro &amp; Phillips, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-39">Sotomayor &amp; Schulten, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-40">Sotomayor et al., 2012</xref>) but have not been tested as rigorously on specific interactions with protein functional groups or structural aspects. Despite these caveats, we believe that the general principles that yield strong binding of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> to the external binding site and the uncompensated energy cost of dehydration that yields the main energy barrier for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> in the pore, are likely arise even with a polarisable force field. However, caution should be applied to making quantitative predictions. It is certainly possible that the <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> parameters influence the ease by which <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> can pass resident <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> ions.</p>
      <p>It is interesting to ponder how changes to NavAb could lead to <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> selectivity. A small number of mutations have been shown to be able to convert bacterial sodium channels into being <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> selective (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-37">Shaya et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-51">Yue et al., 2002</xref>). These involve introducing additional acidic residues at the mouth of the channel, the presence of which seems to be essential for generating <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> selectivity. The additional negative charge may increase the chance of a second <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> entering the pore to yield knock on <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> conduction. The PMF determined here with two <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> in the pore suggests that the presence of multiple divalent ions can reduce the major barrier to <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> seen in our simulations, but given that this barrier arises far from the location of the mutations further simulations will be required to shed light on this issue. The additional negative charge may also accentuate the difference in the binding affinity of the filter for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> compared to <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content>.</p>
      <p>Given that <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> binds more strongly than <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> in NavAb, and experimental studies of eukaryotic calcium channels show they are permanently occupied by <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content>, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-20">Hess &amp; Tsien, 1984</xref>) it is also possible that <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> selectivity could be obtained by preventing <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> from being able to pass a resident <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> ion. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">Figure 8</xref> indicates that such passing is likely to occur in the channel mouth, slightly external to Glu177. So, selectivity for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> over <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> may also be achieved by narrowing the diameter of the pore entrance to create genuinely single file conduction. If such a narrowing took place external to Glu177, it need not significantly change the diameter of the narrow point of the selectivity filter and so could keep this consistent with experimental estimates of the minimum pore diameter in eukaryotic calcium channels (&gt;5.5 Å) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-27">Mccleskey &amp; Almers, 1985</xref>). Similarly, if the Glu177 side chains were less constrained in position by hydrogen bonds to the rest of the protein, then it is possible that multiple side chains would coordinate a passing <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> and occlude the pore as is studies of a model pore (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-50">Yang, Henderson &amp; Busath, 2004</xref>). Site directed mutagenesis and electrophysiology has shown that in calcium channels the four glutamate residues are not symmetrically positioned (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-12">Ellinor et al., 1995</xref>) and it is possible that this would also weaken the binding affinity of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> to the filter to allow conduction to occur more easily.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>In agreement with experimental data, the single and multi-ion free energy profiles calculated here indicate that the <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> conductance of NavAb is likely to be much smaller than for <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content>. While the results presented here signify that the channel will prefer the conduction of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> in mixed solutions, the difference in energy barriers for the conduction of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> in mixed solution are small, in agreement with permeability ratios in the order of 10:1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-51">Yue et al., 2002</xref>). The reason that <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> has difficulty in passing through the pore appears to be due to the limited space midway through the selectivity filter between the sections lined by the Glu177 side chains and the carbonyl backbones of Leu176. The lack of both space and polar groups here limits ion coordination numbers without offering compensating ion–protein interactions. <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> suffers a more significant drop in coordination numbers at this point and thus a larger dehydration penalty than does <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content>. Our results indicate that ions can pass each other in the pore, which is why <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> does not block <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> currents, however our data does predict a larger attenuation of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> currents by <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> than was seen in the related channel NachBac.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>Michael Thomas is thanked for helpful discussions.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="additional-information">
      <title>Additional Information and Declarations</title>
      <fn-group content-type="competing-interests">
        <title>Competing Interests</title>
        <fn id="conflict-1" fn-type="con">
          <p>Ben Corry is an Academic Editor for PeerJ.</p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <fn-group content-type="author-contributions">
        <title>Author Contributions</title>
        <fn id="contribution-1" fn-type="con">
          <p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-1">Ben Corry</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, wrote the paper.</p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>
    </sec>
    <ref-list content-type="authoryear">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref-1">
        <label>Bako, Hutter &amp; Palinkas (2002)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bako</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hutter</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Palinkas</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Car–Parrinello molecular dynamics simulation of the hydrated calcium ion</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Chemical Physics</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>117</volume>
          <fpage>9838</fpage>
          <lpage>9843</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.1517039</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-2">
        <label>Boda et al. (2009)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boda</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valiskó</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Henderson</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eisenberg</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gillespie</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nonner</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ionic selectivity in L-type calcium channels by electrostatics and hard-core repulsion</article-title>
          <source>Journal of General Physiology</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>133</volume>
          <fpage>497</fpage>
          <lpage>509</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.200910211</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-3">
        <label>Bucher &amp; Kuyucak (2008)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bucher</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuyucak</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Polarization of water in the first hydration shell of <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">K<sup>+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> ions</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Physical Chemistry B</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <fpage>10786</fpage>
          <lpage>10790</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jp804694u</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-4">
        <label>Cates, Teodoro &amp; Phillips (2002)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cates</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Teodoro</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Phillips</surname>
              <given-names>GN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular mechanisms of calcium and magnesium binding to parvalbumin</article-title>
          <source>Biophysical Journal</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>1133</fpage>
          <lpage>1146</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3495(02)75472-6</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-5">
        <label>Catterall (2000)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Catterall</surname>
              <given-names>WA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>From ionic currents to molecular mechanisms: the structure and function of voltage-gated sodium channels</article-title>
          <source>Neuron</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>13</fpage>
          <lpage>25</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(00)81133-2</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-6">
        <label>Cibulsky &amp; Sather (2000)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cibulsky</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sather</surname>
              <given-names>WA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The EEEE locus is the sole high-affinity <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> binding structure in the pore of a voltage-gated <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> channel – Block by <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> entering from the intracellular pore entrance</article-title>
          <source>Journal of General Physiology</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>116</volume>
          <fpage>349</fpage>
          <lpage>362</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.116.3.349</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-7">
        <label>Corry et al. (2000)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Corry</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A model of calcium channels</article-title>
          <source>Bba-Biomembranes</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>1509</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0005-2736(00)00330-8</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-8">
        <label>Corry et al. (2001)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Corry</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mechanisms of permeation and selectivity in calcium channels</article-title>
          <source>Biophysical Journal</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>195</fpage>
          <lpage>214</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3495(01)76007-9</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-9">
        <label>Corry &amp; Chung (2006)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Corry</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mechanisms of valence selectivity in biological ion channels</article-title>
          <source>Cellular and Molecular Life Science</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <fpage>301</fpage>
          <lpage>315</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-005-5405-8</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-10">
        <label>Corry &amp; Thomas (2012)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Corry</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mechanism of ion permeation and selectivity in a voltage gated sodium channel</article-title>
          <source>Journal of the American Chemical Society</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>134</volume>
          <fpage>1840</fpage>
          <lpage>1846</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja210020h</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-11">
        <label>Corry, Vora &amp; Chung (2005)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Corry</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vora</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Electrostatic basis of valence selectivity in cationic channels</article-title>
          <source>Bba-Biomembranes</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>1711</volume>
          <fpage>72</fpage>
          <lpage>86</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamem.2005.03.002</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-12">
        <label>Ellinor et al. (1995)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ellinor</surname>
              <given-names>PT</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> channel selectivity at a single-locus for high-affinity <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> interactions</article-title>
          <source>Neuron</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>1121</fpage>
          <lpage>1132</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0896-6273(95)90100-0</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-13">
        <label>Favre, Moczydlowski &amp; Schild (1996)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Favre</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moczydlowski</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schild</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>On the structural basis for ionic selectivity among <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content>, <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">K<sup>+</sup></named-content>, and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> in the voltage-gated sodium channel</article-title>
          <source>Biophysical Journal</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>71</volume>
          <fpage>3110</fpage>
          <lpage>3125</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3495(96)79505-X</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-14">
        <label>French et al. (1994)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>French</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ion permeation, divalent ion block, and chemical modification of single sodium-channels – description by single-occupancy and double-occupancy rate-theory models</article-title>
          <source>Journal of General Physiology</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>447</fpage>
          <lpage>470</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.103.3.447</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-15">
        <label>Furini &amp; Domene (2012)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Furini</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Domene</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>On conduction in a bacterial sodium channel</article-title>
          <source>PLoS Computational Biology</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002476</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-16">
        <label>Gillespie (2008)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gillespie</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Energetics of divalent selectivity in a calcium channel: the ryanodine receptor case study</article-title>
          <source>Biophysical Journal</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>94</volume>
          <fpage>1169</fpage>
          <lpage>1184</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1529/biophysj.107.116798</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-17">
        <label>Goldin (2001)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goldin</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Resurgence of sodium channel research</article-title>
          <source>Annual Review of Physiology</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <fpage>871</fpage>
          <lpage>894</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.physiol.63.1.871</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-18">
        <label>Grossfield (0000)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <person-group>
            <name>
              <surname>Grossfield</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <comment>An implementation of WHAM: the weighted histogram analysis method. <uri xlink:href="http://membrane.urmc.rochester.edu/Software/WHAM/WHAM.html">http://membrane.urmc.rochester.edu/Software/WHAM/WHAM.html</uri> (accessed 26/1/2010)</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-19">
        <label>Heinemann et al. (1992)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Heinemann</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Calcium-channel characteristics conferred on the sodium-channel by single mutations</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>356</volume>
          <fpage>441</fpage>
          <lpage>443</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/356441a0</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-20">
        <label>Hess &amp; Tsien (1984)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hess</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsien</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mechanism of ion permeation through calcium channels</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>309</volume>
          <fpage>453</fpage>
          <lpage>456</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/309453a0</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-21">
        <label>Hille (2001)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hille</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Ion channels of excitable membranes</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <publisher-loc>Sunderland, Mass</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Sinauer</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-22">
        <label>Joung &amp; Cheatham (2008)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Joung</surname>
              <given-names>IS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cheatham</surname>
              <given-names>TE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Determination of alkali and halide monovalent ion parameters for use in explicitly solvated biomolecular simulations</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Physical Chemistry B</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <fpage>9020</fpage>
          <lpage>9041</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jp8001614</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-23">
        <label>Klauda et al. (2010)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Klauda</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Update of the CHARMM all-atom additive force field for lipids: validation on six lipid types</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Physical Chemistry B</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>114</volume>
          <fpage>7830</fpage>
          <lpage>7843</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jp101759q</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-24">
        <label>Kumar et al. (1992)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The weighted histogram analysis method for free-energy calculations on biomolecules. 1. The method</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Computers and Chemistry</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>1011</fpage>
          <lpage>1021</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.540130812</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-25">
        <label>MacKerell et al. (1998)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>MacKerell</surname>
              <given-names>AD</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>All-atom empirical potential for molecular modeling and dynamics studies of proteins</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Physical Chemistry B</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <fpage>3586</fpage>
          <lpage>3616</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jp973084f</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-26">
        <label>Marchand &amp; Roux (1998)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Marchand</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roux</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular dynamics study of calbindin D-9k in the apo and singly and doubly calcium-loaded states</article-title>
          <source>Proteins</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>265</fpage>
          <lpage>284</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0134(19981101)33:2\lt265::AID-PROT10\gt3.0.CO;2-I</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-27">
        <label>Mccleskey &amp; Almers (1985)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mccleskey</surname>
              <given-names>EW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Almers</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Ca channel in skeletal-muscle is a large pore</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>7149</fpage>
          <lpage>7153</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.82.20.7149</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-28">
        <label>McCusker et al. (2012)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McCusker</surname>
              <given-names>EC</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Structure of a bacterial voltage-gated sodium channel pore reveals mechanisms of opening and closing</article-title>
          <source>Nature Communications</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>1102</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms2077</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-29">
        <label>Mozhayeva, Naumov &amp; Khodorov (1982)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mozhayeva</surname>
              <given-names>GN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Naumov</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khodorov</surname>
              <given-names>BI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Potential-dependent blockage of batrachotoxin-modified sodium-channels in frog node of ranvier by calcium-ions</article-title>
          <source>General Physiology and Biophysics</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>281</fpage>
          <lpage>282</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-30">
        <label>Nonner, Catacuzzeno &amp; Eisenberg (2000)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nonner</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Catacuzzeno</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eisenberg</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Binding and selectivity in L-type calcium channels: a mean spherical approximation</article-title>
          <source>Biophysical Journal</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>1976</fpage>
          <lpage>1992</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3495(00)76446-0</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-31">
        <label>Payandeh et al. (2011)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Payandeh</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The crystal structure of a voltage-gated sodium channel</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>475</volume>
          <fpage>353</fpage>
          <lpage>U104</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10238</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-32">
        <label>Payandeh et al. (2012)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Payandeh</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Crystal structure of a voltage-gated sodium channel in two potentially inactivated states</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>486</volume>
          <fpage>135</fpage>
          <lpage>U166</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-33">
        <label>Phillips et al. (2005)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Phillips</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Scalable molecular dynamics with NAMD</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Computers and Chemistry</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>1781</fpage>
          <lpage>1802</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.20289</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-34">
        <label>Ravindran, Schild &amp; Moczydlowski (1991)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ravindran</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schild</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moczydlowski</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Divalent-cation selectivity for external block of voltage-dependent <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> channels prolonged by batrachotoxin – <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Zn<sup>2+</sup></named-content>induces discrete substates in cardiac <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Na<sup>+</sup></named-content> channels</article-title>
          <source>Journal of General Physiology</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <fpage>89</fpage>
          <lpage>115</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.97.1.89</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-35">
        <label>Ren et al. (2001)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ren</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A prokaryotic voltage-gated sodium channel</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>294</volume>
          <fpage>2372</fpage>
          <lpage>2375</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1065635</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-36">
        <label>Root &amp; Mackinnon (1994)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Root</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mackinnon</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>2 identical noninteracting sites in an ion-channel revealed by proton-transfer</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>265</volume>
          <fpage>1852</fpage>
          <lpage>1856</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.7522344</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-37">
        <label>Shaya et al. (2011)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shaya</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Voltage-gated sodium channel (Na-V) protein dissection creates a set of functional pore-only proteins</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>108</volume>
          <fpage>12313</fpage>
          <lpage>12318</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1106811108</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-38">
        <label>Song &amp; Corry (2009)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Song</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Corry</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intrinsic ion selectivity of narrow hydrophobic pores</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Physical Chemistry B</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>113</volume>
          <fpage>7642</fpage>
          <lpage>7649</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jp810102u</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-39">
        <label>Sotomayor &amp; Schulten (2008)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sotomayor</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schulten</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The allosteric role of the <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>(2+)</sup></named-content> switch in adhesion and elasticity of C-cadherin</article-title>
          <source>Biophysical Journal</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>94</volume>
          <fpage>4621</fpage>
          <lpage>4633</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1529/biophysj.107.125591</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-40">
        <label>Sotomayor et al. (2012)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sotomayor</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weihofen</surname>
              <given-names>WA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gaudet</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Corey</surname>
              <given-names>DP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Structure of a force-conveying cadherin bond essential for inner-ear mechanotransduction</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>492</volume>
          <fpage>128</fpage>
          <lpage>132</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11590</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-41">
        <label>Sun et al. (1997)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>YM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>On the structural basis for size-selective permeation of organic cations through the voltage-gated sodium channel – effect of alanine mutations at the DEKA locus on selectivity, inhibition by <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">Ca<sup>2+</sup></named-content> and <named-content content-type="chemical-compound">H<sup>+</sup></named-content>, and molecular sieving</article-title>
          <source>Journal of General Physiology</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>693</fpage>
          <lpage>715</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.110.6.693</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-42">
        <label>Tang et al. (1993)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yatani</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bahinski</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mori</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schwartz</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular localization of regions in the L-type calcium channel critical for dihydropyridine action</article-title>
          <source>Neuron</source>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>1013</fpage>
          <lpage>1021</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0896-6273(93)90215-D</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-43">
        <label>Tanguy &amp; Yeh (1988)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tanguy</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yeh</surname>
              <given-names>JZ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Divalent-cation block of normal and Btx-modified sodium-channels in squid axons</article-title>
          <source>Biophysical Journal</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>A229</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-44">
        <label>Taylor, Armstrong &amp; Bezanilla (1976)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Taylor</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Armstrong</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bezanilla</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Block of sodium channels by external calcium-ions</article-title>
          <source>Biophysical Journal</source>
          <year>1976</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>A27</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3495(76)85660-3</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-45">
        <label>Thomas, Jayatilaka &amp; Corry (2007)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jayatilaka</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Corry</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The predominant role of coordination number in potassium channel selectivity</article-title>
          <source>Biophysical Journal</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <fpage>2635</fpage>
          <lpage>2643</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1529/biophysj.107.108167</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-46">
        <label>Torrie &amp; Valleau (1974)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Torrie</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valleau</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Monte-Carlo free-energy estimates using non-Boltzmann sampling – application to subcritical Lennard-Jones fluid</article-title>
          <source>Chemical Physics Letters</source>
          <year>1974</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>578</fpage>
          <lpage>581</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0009-2614(74)80109-0</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-47">
        <label>Vora, Corry &amp; Chung (2005)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vora</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Corry</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A model of sodium channels</article-title>
          <source>Bba-Biomembranes</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>1668</volume>
          <fpage>106</fpage>
          <lpage>116</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamem.2004.11.011</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-48">
        <label>Woodhull (1973)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Woodhull</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ionic blockage of sodium channels in nerve</article-title>
          <source>Journal of General Physiology</source>
          <year>1973</year>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <fpage>687</fpage>
          <lpage>708</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.61.6.687</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-49">
        <label>Yamamoto, Yeh &amp; Narahashi (1984)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yamamoto</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yeh</surname>
              <given-names>JZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Narahashi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Voltage-dependent calcium block of normal and tetramethrin-modified single sodium-channels</article-title>
          <source>Biophysical Journal</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>337</fpage>
          <lpage>344</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3495(84)84159-4</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-50">
        <label>Yang, Henderson &amp; Busath (2004)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Henderson</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Busath</surname>
              <given-names>DD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Calcium block of sodium current in a model calcium channel: cylindrical atomistic pore with glutamate side chains</article-title>
          <source>Molecular Simulations</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>75</fpage>
          <lpage>80</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0892702031000152244</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-51">
        <label>Yue et al. (2002)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yue</surname>
              <given-names>LX</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The cation selectivity filter of the bacterial sodium channel, NaChBac</article-title>
          <source>Journal of General Physiology</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>120</volume>
          <fpage>845</fpage>
          <lpage>853</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.20028699</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-52">
        <label>Zhang et al. (2012)</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Crystal structure of an orthologue of the NaChBac voltage-gated sodium channel</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>486</volume>
          <fpage>130</fpage>
          <lpage>134</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11054</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
